<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moderate answer vnto Dr. Bastvvicks book; called Independency not Gods ordinance. Wherein is declared the manner how some churches in this city were gathered, and upon what tearmes their members were admitted; that so both the Dr. and the reader may judge, how near some beleevers who walk together in the fellowship of the gospell, do come in their practice to these apostolicall rules which are propounded by the Dr. as Gods method in gethering churches and admitting members. / By Hanserd Knollys. Printed and published according to order. Imprimatur, Ja: Cranford.</title>
            <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87820</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E293_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860964</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860964</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87820)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E293[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moderate answer vnto Dr. Bastvvicks book; called Independency not Gods ordinance. Wherein is declared the manner how some churches in this city were gathered, and upon what tearmes their members were admitted; that so both the Dr. and the reader may judge, how near some beleevers who walk together in the fellowship of the gospell, do come in their practice to these apostolicall rules which are propounded by the Dr. as Gods method in gethering churches and admitting members. / By Hanserd Knollys. Printed and published according to order. Imprimatur, Ja: Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iane Coe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Bastwick, John. Independency not Gods ordinance (Wing B1063, B1069).</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bastwick, John, 1593-1654. --  Independency not Gods ordinance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113091:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Moderate Anſwer VNTO Dr. BASTVVICKS BOOK; CALLED,
<hi>Jndependency not Gods Ordinance.</hi> WHEREIN, Is declared the manner how
ſome CHVRCHES in this City were gathered, and upon what tearmes their Members
were admitted; That ſo both the Dr. and the Reader may judge, how near ſome
Beleevers who walk together in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpell, do come in
their practice to theſe Apoſtolicall rules which are propounded by the Dr.
as Gods method in gathering Churches and admitting MEMBERS.</p>
            <p>By HANSERD KNOLLYS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed and publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JA: CRANFORD.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IANE COE. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113091:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113091:2"/>
            <head>A Moderate ANSWER UNTO Dr. BASTWICKS Book; CALLED,
<hi>Jndependencie not Gods Ordinance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aſſing by many things leſſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, becauſe I
intend brevity; In the 7th. page of the Doctors booke, <hi>There is a twofold
Queſtion betweene them called</hi> PRESBYTERIANS <hi>and their Brethren who
are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> INDEPENDENTS; <hi>The firſt is, concerning the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
of the Church,</hi> viz. <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be</hi> Presbyterian-Dependen,
<hi>or</hi> Presbyterian-Independent? <hi>The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Queſtion is,
concerning the Gathering of</hi> CHURCHES.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:113091:3"/>Touching the former Queſtion concerning the
Government of the Church, the Doctor acknowledgeth in the ſame 7th. page,
<hi>that the Brethren on both ſides agree, that the Government of the church
is a Preſbyterian-Government, both acknowledging a Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</hi> But
whether it be Dependent, or Independent is the maine thing in the queſtion,
which the Doctor doth determine, and ſaith in the Title page of his book he
hath evidently Proved. '<hi>That the Preſbyterian-Government-Dependent is
Gods Ordinance, and not the byterian-Government-Independent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I intend not to ſtrive with the Doctor about wordes, and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore touching the two Termes, to wit, Dependent, and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; I
ſhall onely ſay this at preſent: That if by Independent the the Doctor
indeede mean (as it doth appear ſo to my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by many
paſſages in his booke, he doth intend) a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian-Government, which
hath not Dependencie upon any in matters meerly Eccleſiaſticall (but upon
the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Who is the Head of the Church) And if by Dependent
hee alſo indendeth (as in many other paſſages in his booke ſeemeth to
me to be his meaning)<note place="margin">Pag. 8.10. Pag. 14.15.17.18.</note> a
Presbyterian-Government, which hath a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencie upon a ſupream Judicature
of a Common-councell of Presbyters, and who muſt in matters
Eccleſiaſticall be ſubiect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Decrees, Sentences, Conſtitutions,
and Commandments of a Common-councell, Colledge or Conſiſtorie of
Claſſicall, Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, or Synodicall Presbyters; Then I do conceive the
Doctor hath not proved, (nor will he ever be able to prove) That the
Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian-Government-Dependent is Gods Ordinance; And I hope to make the
contrary plainly appear both from cleere Texts of Scripture, and the Doctors
owne bookes. And ſeeing that the Doctor hath in the 6th. p. of his Book
deſired all his Chriſtan Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the Deciding of this Queſtion to
take the Word of God into their Hands, and with the Noble <hi>Bereans</hi> to
ſit downe and examine, whatſoever ſhall be ſaid on either ſide
according to the Scriptures: I willingly make the ſame requeſt, as moſt
deſirous, that this ſhort Anſwere may abide the like triall, and be
weighed in the other ballance of the Sanctuary againſt the Doctors Booke.</p>
            <p>Now that all things may be handled in good order, and in a 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113091:3"/>Methodicall way, the Doctor hath reduced the whole
diſputation concerning this firſt Queſtion into four Propoſitions,
page. 11. 
<list>
                  <item>The firſt, that there were many Congregations and
ſeverall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Beleevers in the church of Ieruſalem, in the
which they enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all acts of Worſhip, and all the Ordinances amongſt
themſelves, and did partake of all acts of Church-fellowſhip, eſpecially
of preaching, and in the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and prayer, and
that before the Perſecution we reade of, Act. 8.2.</item>
                  <item>The ſecond, That all theſe congregations, and
ſeverall aſſemblies made but one church.</item>
                  <item>The third, That the Apoſtles and Elders governed,
ordered, and ruled this church joyntly, and by a Common-councell, and
Prebſytery.</item>
                  <item>The fourth, that this church of Ieruſalem, and the
government of the ſame is to be a patterne for all ſeverall congregations
and aſſemblies in any City or Vicinity to unite into one Church, and for
the Officers of thoſe congregations to governe that Church joyntly in a
Colledge or Preſbyterie.</item>
               </list> Theſe are his four Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>But before hee comes to the proof of theſe particulars hee
ſaith it will not bee amiſſe in generall to take notice, <hi>That all the
Churches we read of in the New Teſtament, were</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocratically
<hi>and</hi> Preſtbyterially <hi>governed, and were all Dependent upon their
ſeverall</hi> Presbyters, <hi>and produceth divers places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to
prove the ſame,</hi> and two ſheets are ſpent wholly in proving thereof
from the 12. page to the 29. All which (ſhould it bee granted) only proves.
Firſt, That in every City or Church there was a Presbiterie, Acts. 14.23.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cumque per ſuffragia
ſtatuiſſent illis per ſingulas Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſias ſeniores,</hi> that is,
When they had ordained them Elders in every Church by the Suffrage or
ſtretching forth of Hands, alſo <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 1.5.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; conſtituas oppidatim
ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores,</hi> that is, And thou mayeſt Ordaine Elders towne by towne, or
city by city, or village by village.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that as there were Apoſtles and Elders in the Church
of Jeruſalem, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.2,4. So there were Elders in the Church of
Epheſus, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.17,28. And in the Church of Corinth, and in the
Church of Galatia, and in Philippie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that theſe ſeverall Churches were Dependent upon 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113091:4"/>their ſeverall Presbyters, and were to obey them who had
the rule over them, Heb. 13.7,17,24. Or who were their Guides,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Obedite ducibus
veſtris,</hi> that is Obey your Guides.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that this Presbyterian-Church-Government, God hath hath
appointed as his Ordinance, to be continued to the end of the world, the which
whoſoever reſiſteth, reſiſteth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, but it doth not
prove, That this Presbyterian-Church-Government is Dependent upon a ſupreame
Judicature of a Common-counſell of Presbyters, or that they muſt ſubmit,
and ſubject them themſelves and their churches unto the Decrees, Sentences,
Conſtitutions, and Commandements, of a Common-councell, colledge, and court
of claſſicall, or Synodall Presbyters, which the Doctor ſhould have
proved, for ſuch a Presbyterian-Government he intends, as may appeare by the
Doctors owne words, pag. 17.18. <hi>As for the Preſbyterian Government (in
the ſence that I underſtand it) there is nothing more cleare to me in all
the Scripture: Yea the very word and name of Preſbytery ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, a
Magiſtracy, or Ariſtocracy, or Signory, or court. And as the word is taken
in the civill Polity and Government, ſo in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, by a
Preſbytery wee underſtand</hi> (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>page</hi> 18. <hi>A
Religious, Grave, Sollid, Learned, and Wiſe Councell of Divines, Miniſters,
&amp;c. Without whoſe joynt and mutuall accord, or agreement and
common-conſent nothing ought to be done or tranſacted of publicke
concernment. And to make this good,</hi> to wit, That the Presbyters of
particular congregations or aſſemblies of Beleevers, and their Churches
ought to be ſubject to a Common-councell or Court of Presbyters. The Doctor
urgeth that Scripture, the third Epiſtle of John, the 9.10,11. verſes, as
an invincible Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>You ſhall finde it thus expounded by the Doctor pag. 15. 
<q rend="inline">'And therefore when <hi>Diotrephes</hi>
aſſumed to himſelf, and his particular congregation a power and authority
to rule according to his will and pleaſure, without the conſent of the
Presbyterie, and oppoſed <hi>Iohn</hi> the Presbyter, He ſharply reproves
his proceedings, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to the Church; That when he came he would
remember<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113091:4"/>his words, and teach him how to prate againſt the
Presbytery with malicious words; Which is an evill thing in him ſaith St.
<hi>Iohn.</hi> It was evill in him to aſſume unto himſelf, and his
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular congregation, that power that belonged unto the colledge or
councell of Presbyters, and was to be moderated and exerciſed onely by the
conjoynt, and common-conſent of the Presbytery. For God hath appointed, that
the Church ſhould be governed by a Presbytery; and <hi>Diotrephes</hi> would
have his congregation In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent, and have an abſolute jurisdiction within
it ſelf, which ſaith St. <hi>Iohn</hi> is an evill thing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now let the Reader judge, whether the Dr. be not much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
in his Commentary-expoſition and application of this place of Scripture. And
let me give you to underſtand, that St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith verſe 9.
<hi>I wrote unto the Church.</hi> Or as <hi>Beza</hi> upon that verſe,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Scripſi nonnihil
Eccleſiae,</hi> that is, I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſomething to the Church. But
ſeeing no mention is made of any perticular Congregation, how can the Dr.
ſo confidently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that it was his particular Congregation? Now the
Reader may ſee plainly, That the Dr. can expound thoſe Brethren and their
Elders or Presbyters, which the Scripture calles a Church, to be a particular
Congregation. And what it was which St. <hi>Iohn</hi> had written to the Church
is not in this Epiſtle, nor any other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, declared, except it was, to
receive thoſe Brethren, which he ſaith verſe 8. ought to be received, and
verſe 10. whom <hi>Diotrephes</hi> would not receive, how then doth the
Doctor ſay? <hi>That</hi> Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes <hi>aſſumed that power to
himſelf, which belonged unto the Colledge and councell of Presbyters; without
whoſe joynt and mutuall agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and common-conſent nothing ought to be
done or tranſacted of publike concernment.</hi> Is the receiving of Brethren,
or caſting out of Brethren a power which belongs to a Colledge of Presbyters,
and neither the one nor the other may be tranſacted by the Elders and
Brethren of a particular congregation, unleſſe the court or common-councell
of Presbyters conjoyntly conſent unto it? Let it be alſo conſidered, That
<hi>Diotrephes</hi> oppoſed the Brethren and forbade them, that would have
received thoſe, who St. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith verſe 8. we ought to receive,
yea and caſt them ought, verſ. 10.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp; volentes (admittere)
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibet<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113091:5"/>&amp; de Eccleſia dejicit.</hi> That is, and
forbiddeth them, that would (or are willing to admit them) and caſteth them
out of the church, to wit, excommunicates them. Doth it hereby appear that
<hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trephes</hi> would have his congregation Independent? and have an
abſolute jurisdiction within it ſelf. No, but <hi>Diotrephes</hi> would
Lord it over the church, and have the pre-eminence above his brethren, whether
fellow Elders or fellow Saints, verſe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſed amans primatum gerere
in eos Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rephes,</hi> that is, But <hi>Diotrephes</hi> loving the primacie
amongſt them. He would be the Primate and Metropolitan of the church, and
have the Pre-eminence of all the Presbyters in it, and Brethren of it. The
Doctor could have urged this Scripture againſt the domineer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prelates, and
why ſhould he marvail, that his Brethren ſhould now urge it againſt the
court of Presbyters. It is confeſſed <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes</hi> did that which
was evill in uſurping Authority over the church, and thoſe Brethren, whom
he caſt out of the church; But that he was the firſt that oppoſed the
Presbyterian Government, or that he did affront a Court and common-councell of
Presbyters, is more then I know, or the Doctor can prove. For had
<hi>Diotrephes</hi> done ſo, why was he not convented before them, ſurely
the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle and Elder St. <hi>Iohn</hi> would rather have written to the
colledge of Presbyters (if there were any ſuch) then to the Church, or in
writing to the Church, would rather have ſent him a ſummons to appear at
ſome conſiſtorie before the Court and common-councell of Presbyters, then
to warne them to take heed of his evill, that they did not follow it: And
doubtleſſe St. <hi>Iohn</hi> would have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thus, <hi>Diotrephes</hi>
loves to be a Primate among you, wherefore when the Presbyterie that is to
ſay, the Magiſtracy or Signory of grave, ſolid, learned, religious, and
wiſe Divines and Miniſters come to keep order, and met together in a Court
and common-councell, I will remember his deeds, and inform, or complain to the
Court and common-councell of Presbyters, that he prates againſt us (the
Presbyters) with malicious words. But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Iohn</hi> (did not
know any Court or common-councell of Presbyters, neither Claſſicall, nor
Synod call, to appeal unto) [Nor can the Doctor make good thoſe Appeales he
mentioneth pag. 10. to be according to the Scripture of Truth, to wit;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113091:5"/>
               <hi>That every particular man, as well as any Aſſembly or
Congregation, may have their appeal to the Presbyterie of their Precinct,
hundred, or deviſion under whoſe jurisdictions they were; And if they finde
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wronged there, then they have appeales to ſome other higher
Presbytery or Councell of Divines for relief and juſtice.</hi> I onely ask
the Doctor how he can prove theſe appeales by Scripture; and if he could,
whether that higher Presbytery or Councell of Divines, (eſpecially if they
may ſay the Holy Ghoſt and we) be not as Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent as theſe Brethren
and their Churches, againſt whom the Doctor hath written: And if ſo, then
ſuch a high Presbytery or Councell of Divines, is not Gods Ordintnce, by the
Doctors own confeſſion and Affirmation.] Therefore the Apoſtle writes to
the Church or perticular Congregation whereof <hi>Diotrephes</hi> was a Member
and an Elder, whom he knew had power to judge him, as well as the Church or
perticular Congregation of Corinth had power to judge them that were Members
therein. 1 Cor. 5.12.13. And therefore might as warrantably admoniſh
<hi>Diotrephes,</hi> as the Church of <hi>Coloſſe</hi> might
<hi>Arckippus:</hi> Coloſſ. 4.17. 
<q rend="inline">'And if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of publike concernment ought to
bee done or tranſacted without the joynt and mutuall accord or agreement, and
common conſent of the Presbytery;</q> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the Presbyter would not
have tranſgreſſed ſo farre, as to take upon himſelf this Authority
over <hi>Diotrephes</hi> to tell the Church of his faults, and to ſay he
would remember him and ſharply reprove him, and teach him to prate againſt
the Presbyterie with malicious words, which belonged to the Court and Common
Councell of Presbyters: But I ſhall have a juſt occaſion to ſay more
touching this matter in the anſwer unto the third Queſtion, and therefore
paſsing by the objection with its anſwer mentioned <hi>page</hi> 19. to the
29. unto its due place. I ſhall deſire ſeriouſly to conſider the
Doctors proof of his firſt propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he laboureth firſt by
producing ſuch Scriptures, as he conceiveth make for the manifeſtation of
the Truth, and from thence frames and formeth his Arguments. 
<q rend="inline">'His Scriptures are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Matth.
3. verſ. 1.2.5.6. Mark. 6.20.21. Matth. 14.5. and Luk. 20.4.6.</q> And divers
other Scriptures, which you have at large ſet down in the Doctors Book with
his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments framed from thence, pag. 29. to 82. where this firſt
propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition endeth. The ſumme of all which, I ſhall give the Reader to
underſtand as briefly as I can, to wit; 
<q rend="inline">'Where there was an infinite<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113091:6"/>multitude of Beleevers, or a very City of Beleevers, ſo that they
kept a tyrannicall King in awe, and all the Magiſtrates and Elders in whoſe
hands was all the power and Authority, even a world of Beleevers, with many
Rulers and men of great place and and Office, with ſuch an increaſe of
multitudes of Beleevers, 8000 new Converts beſides women and children, yea
many 10000, of Beleevers, and where there were almoſt an hundred Preachers
and Miniſters, beſides the 12. Apoſtles, and all theſe continually
taken up in Prayer and Preaching, There muſt of neceſſitie be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Congregations and Aſſemblies. But in the Church of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem there was
an infinite multitude of Beleevers, and a very City of Beleevers (which kept
<hi>Herod</hi> himſelf, the tyrant in awe, and all the Magiſtrates and
Elders) even a world of Beleevers, with many Rulers and men of great place and
Office, with an increaſe of multitudes of Beleevers, and 8000. new Converts
beſides wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children, yea and many 10000. after all the
perſecutions, and almoſt an hundred Preachers and Miniſters beſides the
12 A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and all theſe were continually taken up in Prayer and
Preaching; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they muſt of neceſſitie be diſpierſed into
many Congregations and ſeverall Aſſemblies.</q> I do deny the Minor
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this Argument. Neither hath the Doctor proved, That there was
an infinite number of Beleevers, nor a very City of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers in the Church of
Jeruſalem. The Scriptures quoted by the Doctor ſpeakes no ſuch thing;
thoſe places in <hi>Matthew, Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> tell us of very
many who were baptized by <hi>Iohn,</hi> and by Chriſts Diſciples, but do
not declare how many of theſe baptized perſons were of the Church in
Jeruſalem; and the Scripture wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth Acts 9.31. that there were
Churches throughout all Judaea, as well as in Jeruſalem, and for ought I
know, or the Doctor ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, many of thoſe baptized perſons might be in
theſe Churches, yea the moſt of them, and but a few, it may be no more but
thoſe 120. mentioned Acts 1.13,14,15. To whom were added about 3000. ſouls,
who continued in the Apoſtles Doctrine, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and in breaking of
bread and in prayers. Acts 2.41.42.44.46. And as for the world of Beleevers
mentioned in another argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment drawn from Joh. 12.19. behold the world is gone
after him.<note place="margin">Pag. 37 and 40.</note> That Scripture doth not
ſay they beleeved in him, much leſſe that there was a world of Beleevers
in the Church in Ieruſalem. Neither is there mention in any Scripture quoted
by the Doctor of <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113091:6"/>8000. new Converts beſides women and
children. Neither doth that Scripture produced Acts 4.4 prove any ſuch thing:
For the Reader may conſider that the number of them there mentioned are but
5000. And albeit the Doctor make them up 8000. by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe 5000. men
were added to the Church, and joyned to the formers Beleevers pag. 57. Yet
there is a twofold miſtake in the Doctors Addition, to wit; Firſt, that
ſome of the 3000. (may be) were women, and how then can the Doctor ſay,
there were 8000. new converts beſides women. Secondly, theſe 5000. are
onely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led men and not converts, not beleevers. For howbeit many of them
hearing the Word beleeved, yet it is not ſaid the 5000. men beleeved: And the
truth is the Text well conſidered only holds forth, that, the number of men
was made up five thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp; factus
eſt numerus viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quaſi millia quinque,</hi> and the number of men was
made about five thouſand, not 8000. And as for the many 10000<abbr>s.</abbr>
mentioned Acts 21.20. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> comes of
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>infinitus</hi> (and though
the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> do ſometimes
ſignifie <hi>numerum decem millium,</hi> yet not alwayes, but for ſome
great number which cannot ſuddenly be told) as Luke 12 1. And <hi>Beza</hi>
both according to the old and new verſion of the Greek into Latine, reads it
<hi>millia</hi> 1000<abbr>s.</abbr> not <hi>decem millia</hi>
10000<abbr>s.</abbr> and ſo we have it in our Engliſh Bibles tranſlated
thouſands. And the following verſe 22. will make it probable that there
were not many 10000<abbr>s.</abbr> for there we thus read; The multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
muſt needs come together, ſo that I ſay its probable, that they were not
ſo many 1000<abbr>s.</abbr> but they could, yea muſt aſſemble
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Neither can the Dr. make good from thoſe Scriptures he produceth 
<q rend="inline">'pag. 62. to wit, Acts 1. verſ. 21.22. cap. 6.
verſ. 2.4. and cap. 8. verſ. 1. That there was almoſt a hundred Preachers
and Miniſters beſides the 12. Apoſtles in the Church of Jeruſalem.</q>
The 12. are named indeed in Act. 6.2.4. but not 100. beſides, no nor any one
Preacher but them 12. And as for the other two places Acts 1.21.22. and Acts
8.1. there is not any word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Preachers or Miniſters, onely ſome
directions touching the choiſe of <hi>Matthias,</hi> who was one of the 12.
mentioned Act. 6.2. And although they who were ſcattered preached the Word
Acts 8.4. yet the Scripture doth not declare that they were Preachers or
Miniſters of the Church in Jeruſalem.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor hath one Argument, which is more to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113091:7"/>then all the other, which I deſire the Reader
ſeriouſly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, pag. 64. he thus further argueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That, which the Holy Scripture in expreſſe wordes, and in
divers places hath declalred unto us, that every Chriſtian is bound to
beleeve. But the Scripture in expreſſe words, and in diverſe, places hath
decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto us, that there were divers aſſemblies, and Congregations of
Beleevers in the Church of Ieruſalem, and that the Apoſtles, and all the
Beleevers in Ieruſalem, did continue daily with one accord in the Temple, and
that they brake bread from houſe to houſe: and that daily in the Temple,
and in every houſe, they ceaſad not to teach and preach Ieſus
Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ergo, <hi>There was diverſe congregations, and ſeverall
aſſemblies, of Beleevers in the</hi> CHURCH <hi>of Ieruſalem, where they
did duly pertake in all the Ordinances, and injoyed all the acts of
Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I doe deſire the Reader to conſider how the Doctor Proves
his Minor, <hi>which he ſaith is manifeſt from</hi> Acts 2.46. <hi>and
chap.</hi> 5.12,42. <hi>and chap.</hi> 3.11.12. <hi>and many more places, that
might be produced, pag.</hi> 64.65.66. In all which diſcourſe, the Dr.
gives you nothing, but his own ſuppoſitions, and concluſions, for the
proof of his <hi>Minor</hi> propoſition which is his manner of
diſcour-throughout his booke.</p>
            <p>This argument I anſwer; Firſt, by denying the Aſſumption,
or Minor propoſition, and the reaſon of my denying all, is becauſe the
Scriptures produced by the Doctor, doe not in expreſſe words declare, that
there were diverſe aſſemblies, and Congregations of beleevers in the
Church of Jeruſalem, The Scriptures quoted do in expreſſe words declare
the contrary to what the Doctor would prove; For, Acts 2.44,46. All that
beleeved were together, and they continued daily with one accord in the Temple.
and Acts. 3.11,12. It is expreſſely ſaid; That all the people ranne
together to them, in the porch, which is called <hi>Solomons.</hi> Act. 5.12.
And they were all with one accord in <hi>Solomons</hi> Porch. So that theſe
Scriptures produced by the Doctor to prove, that there were divers
aſſemblies and Congregations of Beleevers in the Church of Jeruſalem, who
met together in ſeverall places, at one and the ſame time, to wit, upon the
firſt day of the week, where they did partake daily in all Ordinances, doth
expreſly proove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, to wit, that the Apoſtles, and all the
Beleevers in the Church of Jeruſalem, met together with one accord, in one
place, to wit,<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113091:7"/>the Temple, and in <hi>Solomons Porch,</hi>
and brake bread from houſe to houſe,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Domatius,</hi> not
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>per ſingulas domos,</hi>
and thus they did <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>quotidie,</hi> day by day, and they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtedfaſtly in the
Apoſtles doctrine, and fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and in
prayers, and all that beleeved were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Acts. 2.42,44,46. Yea, the
Doctor himſelfe ſaith in his <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, the latter part
of it. <hi>That the Apoſtles and all the Beleevers in Ieruſalem did
continue daily with one accord in the Temple, and that they brake bread from
houſe to huſe:</hi> And this ſhall ſuffice for refutation of What the
Docter hath Written touching the firſt Propoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond now followes page 81. viz. That all the
Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and ſeverall Aſſemblies made but one Church. And to this
the Doctor ſaith, the Brethren themſelves acknowledge, that all Beleevers
in Jeruſalem were all members of that Church, and they accord further, that
it was but one Church. And it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt out of the Holy Scripture, Acts
2.3.45.46. chapters. To which I alſo conſent; But the Brethren have not
acknowledged, neither hath the Doctor by Scripture proved, that in this one
Church of Jeruſalem there were averſe Congregations and ſeverall
Aſſemblies of Beleevers; and therein I muſt mnnifeſt my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
from the Doctors opinion, promiſing him, that whenſoever he ſhall
ſoundly prove it by expreſſe Words of Scripture (which he hath
undertaken) I will acknowledge it.</p>
            <p>The third propoſition, which the Doctor comes next to prove, is,
<hi>That thee Apoſtles and Elders, or Preſbyters governed, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,
and ruled this Church joyntly and by a common councell and Preſbytery,
pag.</hi> 82. <hi>Which the Doctor ſaith is evident by theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
following: Acts</hi> 11.27. <hi>to the end.</hi> The words of this Sccripture
which the Doctor makes uſe of, to prove his Aſſertion, are theſe,
Verſe 30. <hi>And ſent it to the Elders by the hands of</hi> Barnabas,
<hi>and</hi> Saul. <hi>Here in theſe laſt words</hi> (ſaith the Doctor)
<hi>We ſee, that the Presbyters, and none but the Presbyters received the
Almes, which ſufficiently proveth, that the Presbyters in all Churches were,
the men of Government: pag.</hi> 82. It is not denied by the Brethren, that the
Presbyters in all Churches were the men in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churches in
which they are Elders. But this I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive (by the Doctors favour) doth not
prove it, to wit; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Almes was ſent to the Elders. Much leſſe
doth that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113091:8"/>prove, that the Apoſtles and
Presbyters governed and ruled the Church in Jeruſalem by a Common-councell
and Presbyterie, which is the Aſſertion that the Doctor undertakes to
prove. <hi>But in the</hi> 15. <hi>Chapter verſe</hi> 2.4.6.22. <hi>and in
chap.</hi> 16.4. <hi>And in Acts</hi> 21.17,18. <hi>The Preſbyters of
Ieruſalem by name (ſaith the Doctor pag.)</hi> 83. <hi>are
expreſſed.</hi> Out of which places of Scripture before the Doctor frame
his Arguments, he pleaſeth to make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from page 48. to 90.
Wherein he highly extols the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, making them equall with the
Apoſtles in all the Acts of Church-Governement, (as appeares by the Doctors
owne words, pag. 88. <hi>I doe verily beleeve (ſaith the Doctor) that the
Presbyters did act as authoritively as the Apoſtles: and that the
Preſbyters might as well conclude, It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and
to us, as well as the Apoſtles, and not onely the preſbyters, who ſate in
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell with the Apoſtles, and other preſbyters, who were Ordained
El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by the Apoſtles; And the Aſſemblie now of Divines, or any other,
may congregate and meet together in ſome one place, for the deciding of
controverſies, and differences of opinions in Religion, to ſtate the
Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, and debate them from Scripture, or warrantable authority and
evidence of reaſon deduced from thence, and may determine the qeſtion by
joynt conſent, or by the moſt voyces, and may ſay it ſeemed good to the
Holy Ghoſt, and us. pag.</hi> 87.88.<note place="margin">Pag. 88.</note>
               <hi>And that Preſbiters have their authoritie as well grounded in the Word of
God, as Kings and States have theirs, page.</hi> 89. And the Doctor doth more
eſpecially extoll the Presbyters of this kingdom in theſe our dais, telling
what they have deſerved from the Church, Parliament, and Kingdome more then
any of their Predeceſſors, having ended his Digreſſion, hee gives you
his Argument, pag. 90. To wit: 
<q rend="inline">'They that in the holy Scripture are called
Presbyters, and acted and ordered things in a joynt body, and Common-counſell
with the Presbyters, and exerciſed that ordinary power committed to them in
the 18. of <hi>Mattew,</hi> they acted as Presbyters. But the Apoſtles in
governing the Church of Jeruſalem, conſiſting of many Congregations and
Aſſemblies, acted and ordered things in a joynt body and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon councell
with the Presbytery of that Church, as Presbyters. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church of
Jeruſalem was Presbyterianly governed, and by a Common councell of
Presbyters. The <hi>Major,</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> of this Sillogiſme being
proved (ſaith the Doctor) the concluſion will neceſſarily enſue.</q>
I know not that the Brethren<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113091:8"/>ever denied, That the Church of
Jeruſalem was Presbyterianly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned; And although the Dr. be pleaſed to
make that his conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet (under Reformation be it ſpoke) that
concluſion doth not follow upon the premiſes. For if the Dr. pleaſe to
review his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, He ſhall finde, Firſt; that the ſubject of his
<hi>Major</hi> propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is left out both in his <hi>Minor,</hi> and in
his Concluſion: The firſt part of the Doctors <hi>Minor</hi> ſhould have
beene this, to witt, But the Apoſtles in the holy Scripture are called
Presbyters, and who ever denyed this; Alſo the firſt part of the Doctors
concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould have been this, from theſe two premiſes, to witt;
<hi>Ergo,</hi> The Apoſtles acted as Presbyters which Concluſion is not the
thing in Queſtion. Secondly, that from the ſecond part of the Doctors two
propoſitions (to wit, They that acted and Ordered things in a joynt body and
Common-councell, which the Presbyters, acted as Presbyters; But the Apoſtles
in governing the Church of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem acted and Ordered things in a joynt
body, and Common-councell with the Presbytery, (or Presbyters either) of that
Church: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Apoſtles acted as Presbyters.) This ſhould have
been the Doctors concluſion.</p>
            <p>Now the truth is, though the Apoſtles were called Presbyters in
the Scripture, yet it followeth not, that they acted as Presbyters, but as
Apoſtles Acts 15. And they cannot therein be a pattern and preſident for
Presbyters; Firſt, becauſe the Apoſtles had the care and charge of and
over all Churches. 2 Cor. 11.28. But the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters had the care and
overſight of ſome one Church onely, as Epheſus Acts 20.28. or Philippi,
Phil. 1.1. and this the Dr. often inſerts in his Book. That all the Churches
we read of in the new Teſtament (though they were Presbyterially governed)
were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent upon their ſeverall Presbyters, pag. 12.<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> And ſecondly, becauſe this would make the
Presbyters Independents indeed, for ſo the Apoſtles were in the Government
of all the Churches; The Presbyters of Jeruſalem, of Epheſus, and of all
the Churches were dependent upon the Apoſtles, and the Apoſtles onely
depended on Chriſt, by whoſe holy ſpirit, they were all alwayes guided in
the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their Churches, and therefore they ſaid Acts 15.28. It
ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and us. And though the Doctor ſay the
Presbyters might ſay ſo, as well as the Apoſtles becauſe the Elders or
Presbyters are mentioned there: The Dr. might have alſo conſidered that the
Brethren, even the whole church, the multitude (how many ſoever the D. can
make of them) were preſent as wel as<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113091:9"/>the Presbyters. Acts
15.4.12.22.23.25.27.28. And ſo have made the Brethren, the multitude, even
the whole Church Independent alſo; and the Dr. might as well have affirmed,
that the Brethren even the whole Church might ſay, It ſeemed good to the
Holy Ghoſt and to us.</p>
            <p>To the fourth propoſition; 
<q rend="inline">'That the Church of Jeruſalem and the Government
of the ſame, is to be a pattern for all Congregations and Aſſemblies in
any City or vicinity to unite into one Church, and for the Officers and
Presbyters of thoſe congregations to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern that Church joyntly in a
Colledge or Presbytery. pag. 97.</q> And for the proof of this fourth
Propoſition, the Doctor ſaith; 
<q rend="inline">'That all men acknowledge, that the mother Church
muſt give an example of Government to all the Daughter Churches. Neither do
the Brethren deny (ſaith the Dr.) but the Government of the Church of
Jeruſalem muſt be the pattern of Government to all Churches.</q> But the
Dr. knowes, that the Brethren deny that the Church of Ieruſalem conſiſted
of divers Congregations and ſeverall aſſemblies under a Common-councell,
Conſiſtory, Colledge, or Court of Presbyters. And this they have not
granted, neither hath the Doctor proved. And this may be ſufficient to be
ſaid in anſwer to the four Propoſitions touching the firſt
queſtion.</p>
            <p>And now I come to the ſecond Queſtion, which is concerning the
manner of gathering of Churches, and admitting of Members and Officers pag. 98.
which Queſtion the Dr. thus ſtates, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">'Whether Miniſters of the Goſpell may, out of
already gathered aſſemblies of Beleevers, ſelect and chuſe the moſt
principle of them into a Church-fellowſhip peculiar unto themſelves, and
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of none into their ſociety,</q> but ſuch as ſhall enter in by a
pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Covenant, and are allowed by the conſent, and approbation of all the
Congregation? And this Queſtion the Doctor brancheth into ſixe Queries pag.
98.99. Wherein the judicious Reader may perceive the Doctor (through
miſ-information I conceive) hath miſtaken the ſtateing of the Queſtion,
which he partly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth pag. 100.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">'But now I ſhall ſet down (ſaith the Dr.
pag. 100) Gods me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and the Apoſtles practice in gathering of Churches,
and the manner they uſed in making Members in every Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it
with the method our Brethren (the Independents) uſe, &amp;c.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113091:9"/>And to this purpoſe the Doctor begins with Chriſts
commiſsion, Matth. 28.19,20. and Mark. 16.15,16. and Acts
26.15,16.17,18,19,20.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Out of theſe ſeverall Scriptures the Doctor obſerves theſe
three things, pag. 101. and 102. To wit, Firſt, 
<q rend="inline">'That they ſhould teach no other things but what
Chriſt commanded them, and appeared to them in, and for which thy had his
Word and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Secondly, the condition, which they were to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound unto
all nations and people, upon which they were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church, was
Faith, Repentance, and Baptiſme. And thirdly, that this commiſſion was
delivered onely to the Apoſtles and Miniſters of the Goſpel, that they
ſhould admit whoſoever beleeved, and were baptized; And they that beleeved
not would not be baptized, were not to be admitted. Theſe are the Doctors
owne words, page 102. and page. 103. The Doctor for proofe quotes the third
Chapter of Matthew, and Luke 3.7. And the ſum of <hi>Iohns</hi> preaching
(ſaith the Dr.) is mentioned, verſe 3. It was the baptiſme of Repentance
for the Remiſſion of ſinnes. Alſo he there cites Luke 7.29. That all
the people that heard him, and the Publicans juſtified God, being Baptized
with the Baptiſme of <hi>Iohn;</hi> But the Phariſees and the Lawyers
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the councell of God againſt themſelves, being no Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of
him. page 103.104. But now to go on (ſaith the Dr. pag 104.) after the
Reſurrection and Aſſenſion of Chriſt, &amp;c. Where he quotes, Acts
2.37,38. Then they that gladly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Word were Baptized, and the ſame
day were added unto them about three thouſand ſoules.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hence the Doctor obſerves, that the Apoſtles propounded no
other condition or termes for the making all and every one of them members of
the Church, but Repentance and Baptiſme, <hi>The which, when the people had
accepted of (ſaith the Doctor) They were forthwith admitted, &amp;c.
page.</hi> 104. For another proofe the Doctor produceth, Acts 10.44,47,48.
Where the Doctor affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, page 106. <hi>That thoſe Brethren who came
with</hi> Peter <hi>did not intermeddle in that buſineſſe, to wit, of
their admittance (by Baptiſme) into the Church.</hi> Now I conceive the
reaſon, why thoſe Brethren did not intermeddle to hinder their admittance
to that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113091:10"/>of Jeſus Chriſt, (to wit, Baptiſme
in water) and ſo to an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Church; was, not becauſe they had
not ſuch Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but becauſe the Brethren had no juſt objections or
kindrance to declare to <hi>Peter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Brethren had a liberty to have declared any thing, which
might juſtly have hindred the adminiſtration of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of
Baptiſme unto them, doth appeare by the Queſtion which the Apoſtle
expounded. verſe 47. <hi>Can any man forbid water that theſe ſhould not
be baptized?</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">'And the Dr. himſelfe acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, pag. 102.
That the Brethren or Diſciples of the Church of Jeruſalem (who muſt be a
patterne (ſaith the Dr.) of all churches) had this libertie to except
againſt ſome ſorts of perſons, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their admittance into the
church, though baptized according to Chriſts Commiſſion, and Preachers
choſen and ſent by Chriſt himſelfe. And that in caſe ſuch perſons
have been formerly known to be open Enemies, and perſecuters of the church,
and then they are juſtly to bee ſuſpected (ſaith the Dr. page. 102.)
untill they have given publike Evidence by witneſſe to the Miniſters of
their true Converſion,</q> and there produceth a plaine inſtance to prove
this page 102. Acts. 9.26,27,28. <hi>And when</hi> Saul <hi>was come to
Ieruſalem</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tentabat jungi)
<hi>he aſſayed to joyne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Diſciples, but they were all
afraid of him, and beleeved not that hee was a Diſciple, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this liberty have all the diſciples in the like caſe,
becauſe Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem the Mother church is the pattern of all other the
Daughter Churches, as the Doctor confeſſeth, yea affirmeth, page 97.
<hi>And ſaith, all men acknowledge, That the Mother Church muſt give an
example of government to all the Daughter churches. And this is alſo by the
Doctor acknowledged, page</hi> 102. <hi>to be a part of the power of the Keyes,
to open and ſhut the doores of the Church; that is, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch as are
for their Faith, Knowledge and Repentance ſufficiently qualified, and fitted
to be made members, and to refuſe ſuch, as are not fit to be recived into
the fellowſhip of the church; either for their Ignorance or other ſins and
offences, &amp;c.</hi> Now, then when it doth evidently appear. That the
Diſciples or Brethren (not to ſay Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, though they are Diſciples
alſo) of the Church in Jeruſalem (in her moſt flouriſhing condition)
had this libertie to declare<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113091:10"/>their feares, and the ground
thereof againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> who was at that time a Beleever, a Baptized
perſon, &amp; a Preacher, or miniſter of the Goſpell, ſo that although,
hee came, and aſſayed, to be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Diſciples, and be admitted a
member among them, that he might have fellowſhip with them in the worſhip,
and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Goſpell: Yet was thereby hindered from admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
untill <hi>Barnabas</hi> witneſſed his condition and converſation to the
Apoſtle, and then he was with them coming in &amp; going out at Jeruſalem.
How can the Doctor make good, that 
<q rend="inline">'The Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters alone without the conſent of
Brethren may admit members, and caſt out members, and that the Brethren or
the congregation hath nothing to doe to hinder any ſuch thing, page
102.106.</q>
            </p>
            <p>For further proof hereof: 
<q rend="inline">'The Doctor urgeth <hi>Act.</hi> 8.35. to 40. The
example of the Eunuch, to whom <hi>Philip</hi> being ſent preached Jeſus,
and Baptiſme in his Name, and it is related, That when they came to a
certaine water the Eunuch ſaid unto him; <hi>See here is Water? What doth
hinder me to be Baptized? And</hi> Philip <hi>ſaid, If thou beleeveſt with
all thy heart thou mayeſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>licet,</hi> And he anſwered and ſaid, I beleeve that Jeſus Chriſt
is the Son of God: And he commanded the Charet to ſtand ſtill; And they
went downe both into the water, both <hi>Philip</hi> and the Eunuch, and he
Baptized him. Here we ſet (ſaith the Doctor) that PHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIP admits him into
the number of beleevers, and makes him a member of the Church. But the Doctor
ſaith, this was without conſulting with the Congregation, by his owne
authority, and upon the Eunuch his own teſtimonie, pag. 106.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, that PHILIP had a ſpeciall command from God for what
he did herein, and ſo had <hi>Ananias, Act.</hi> 9.15. touching
<hi>Saul,</hi> which is the next Inſtance which the Doctor brings in this
ſame 106. pag. And albeit the Doctor affirme; 
<q rend="inline">'That ANANIAS did not ſay to SAUL, I will
conſult with the Church to ſee whither they will admit thee to be a member,
for thou haſt greatly waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Church, and made havock of the Saints,
and therefore I will have their approbation, and conſent, and thou ſhalt
give in evidences of thy true Converſion, &amp;c.</q> And ſo be received
and admitted.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113091:11"/> 
               <q rend="inline">'But without all this ado (ſaith the Dr. pag.
107.) he baptized <hi>Paul,</hi> and admitteth him into the number of
Beleevers, and makes him a Member of the Church.</q> Yet if the Reader look
back into the 102. page of his Book, The Dr. there makes an exception from the
power which he a little before had affirmed the Presbyters have to admit
Members, by vertue of Chriſt his commiſſion, upon the profeſſion of
their faith and repentance, and receiving bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, without any further
Teſtimony; 
<q rend="inline">'Unleſſe (ſaith the Dr.) they had been
formerly known to be open enemies, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Church, and then
they were juſtly to be ſuſpected, till they had given publike evidence by
witneſſe of their true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: And gives an inſtance in
<hi>Paul,</hi> who for a time the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples feared Acts 9.26.27. till they
had better information, and proof, that he now preached the faith, that he had
once perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and had ſuffered for it, pag. 102.</q> To rehearſe all
the Scriptures alledged to prove this method of God and practiſe of the
Apoſtles were needleſſe. But paſſing by ſuch as are not ſo plain
and clear for the proof thereof, and alſo omitting, what the Doctor hath
ſaid touching the Brethren, in comparing their practiſe with the
Apoſtles: Becauſe the Dr. is miſtaken in ſtateing the Queſtion, and
alſo in his Queries, as before I mentioned in the 14 page of this my
anſwer, and the Reader may ſee pag. 98 99. and 100. of the Doctors Book. I
ſhall give the Reader the reſult of all, that the Dr. hath written from
pag. 100. to the end of his Book, touching Gods method, and the Apoſtles
practice in gathering of Churches and admitting Members, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">'Firſt, That Chriſt having given a
Commiſſion to his Apoſtles to teach all Nations, and baptize them, Matth.
28.19.20. Mark. 16 15 16. the Apoſtles practiſed accordingly. <hi>Acts</hi>
2.37.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44.45.46.47.48. and ſo did Philip <hi>Acts</hi>
8.35.36.37.38. and Ananias <hi>Acts</hi> 9.10.18. Secondly, That the condition
or tearmes, which they were to propound unto all Nations and people upon which,
they were to be admitted into the Church, were Faith, Repentance, and
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Mark. 16.15,16. For the commiſſion was delivered to the
Apoſtles, that they ſhould admit whoſoever beleeved, and would be
baptized, and they, that beleeved not, and would not be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, were not to
be admitted, pag. 102. and pag. 104. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113091:11"/>(ſaith the Dr.) propounded no other condition or tearmes for making
all and every one Members of the Church but Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Baptiſme,
<hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.38. Thirdly, that the Apoſtles and all ſucceeding
Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhould admit whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever beleeved, and were
baptized, to be Members of the Church, and teach them to obſerve no other
things but what Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, and for which they had his Word and
warrant: pag. 101. and 102. Matth. 28.19.20. And this (ſaith the Dr.) the
Apoſtles did practice, without requiring them to take a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate covenant, or
enter into the Church by way of a particular covenant, pag. 105. <hi>Acts</hi>
2.37.38.</q> This being the ſumme and reſult of that method and practice,
which the Dr. conceives ſhould be done in gathering Churches and admitting
Members, which the Scriptures will warrant, and Chriſt Jeſus approve of as
his fathers will, I ſhall now take liberty to declare, what I know by mine
own experience to be the practice of ſome Churches of God in this City. That
ſo both the Dr. and the Reader may judge how near the Saints, who walk
together in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpell do come in their practice, to
theſe Apoſtolicall rules and practice propounded by the Dr. as Gods method
in gathering Churches, and admitting Members. I ſay, that I know by mine own
experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (having walked with them) That they were thus gathered;
<hi>viz.</hi> Some godly and learned men of approved guifts and abilities for
the Miniſterie, being driven out of the Countries, where they lived by the
perſecution of the Prelates, came to ſojourn in this great City, and
preached the Word of God both publikely, and from houſe to houſe, and daily
in the Temples and in every houſe, they ceaſed not to teach and preach
Jeſus Chriſt: and ſome of them have dwelt in their own hired houſes,
and received all that came in unto them, preaching the Kingdome of God, and
teaching thoſe things, which concern the Lord Jeſus Chriſt. 
<note place="margin">Matth. 28.18.19.20. Mark. 16.15. Act. 8.4.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.19 20.21.22. Act. 10.20.21. Act. 5.42. Act. 28.23.30.31.
Acts 17.1.2,3,4,5. Acts 17.5.11,12. Acts 2.38.40,41,42.</note> And when many
ſinners were converted by their preaching of the Goſpell, ſome of them
that beleeved, conſorted with them, and of profeſſors a great many, and
of the chief women not a few. And the condition which thoſe Preachers both
publikely and privately propounded to the people, unto whom they Preached, upon
which they were to be admitted into the Church was Faith, Repentance, and
Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme;<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113091:12"/>and none other. And whoſoever (poor as well
as rich, bond as well as free, ſervants as well as Maſters) did make a
profeſſion of their Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, and would be baptized with
water into the Name of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Spirit, were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
Members of the Church; but ſuch as did nor beleeve, and would not be baptized
they would not admit into Church-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. 
<note place="margin">Act. 16.30,31,32,33. Acts 8.35.37.38,39. Acts
8.12. Acts 18.8.</note> This hath been the practice of ſome Churches of God
in this City, without urging or making any particular covenant with Members
upon admittance, which I deſire may be examined by the Scriptures cited in
the Margent, and then compared with the Doctors three concluſions from the
ſame Scriptures, whereby it may appear to the judicious Reader, how near the
Churches ſome of them come to the practice of the Apoſtles rule, and
practice of the primitive Churches, both in gathering, and admitting Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.
And my humble requeſt to the Doctor is; That he will uſe all meanes, that
the method of God, and practice of the Apoſtles in gathering of Churches, and
admitting Members, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionably practiſed by his Brethren of both
ſides according to the revealed Word and Will of the Father.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113091:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
